Hello, and welcome to a code walkthrough for Python for Everybody.
We are working through the very first lesson about installing Python.
Now, you don't have to install Python to begin the course, but
eventually you probably want to have Python installed on your computer so
that you can do the more complicated assignments later in the course.
And so we're going to set up, in this case,
we're going to be setting up a Python environment on the Macintosh, okay?
So, but the interesting thing is is that Python
is pre-installed in most modern versions of the Macintosh.
So I'm going to run the terminal.
So I just hit the open tool, and I'm going to start the terminal program.
Now, I always keep the terminal program in my doc cuz I use it so much.
I'll make it a little bigger here.
And so the first thing to do is to figure out which Python versions of Python 3 you
have, so the quickest way to do this is type Python 3.
Oops, and then press the Tab key.
And the fact that it's spaced over means that there is a Python 3 application on
our system.
And so, print hello world.
This is the, this is the, the chevron, the chevron prompt is,
says we're in the Python interpreter.
To get out of that, you type quit.
Okay, so we're out of that.
Now, we can ask the version of Python, this is, I mean, this is Python 3.9 and
it came on my Mac OS 26.1, I think is what I'm running on here.
But you may want to run a more recent version of Python.
So I'm going to go to the Python website, and
I'm going to download Python 3.14, so 3.9 is what's on my computer.
And 3.14, you can use this course,
anything actually more modern than the 3.8, I believe.
So I'm going to install this, it's going to install on my computer.
So it's telling me open SSL and certificate,
it's going to tell me there's a thing I'm supposed to click, it's a little funky.
I'll show you when we get there.
By the way, you're going to meet Guido in this class.
If you keep going, you'll see videos of him, there are several videos with Guido.
So let's go ahead and install it.
I'm going to type my password off screen.
And so now the installation starts.
And it doesn't take too long to get this thing installed.
I mean, the Python org installer is pretty nice, you can keep multiple versions.
Now, idle is an editor that it built in.
I don't know, I don't like it as much as it could.
I'll show you a different way, I'd rather use a real program editor.
It told us to run this install certificates commands, and
this is going to run a script to set a few things up so that security works well.
And so it did that, that was all it did, it added some certificates so
that when you talked in Python to SSL sites.
So we did our certificates, and we're going to close.
And so we're going to move the installer, that's not Python itself,
it's the thing we downloaded to install Python.
So at this point, there's this thing called the path.
And this new Python may or may not be showing up in the path.
So I am going to quit the terminal, and I'm going to start a new terminal.
So I start a new port, and that just re-checks to see anything we've installed
recently, make sure it's in the path.
And if you recall, before I did this Python, I typed Python 3 and then the Tab key.
Now you see that there's a couple of versions.
You see the original Python 3, which if we ran that, Python 3 minus minus version.
You would see that that Python is 3.14, and so you can always add the version.
If you have multiple, oops.
If you have multiple ones, you can type Python 3.14 minus minus version.
It'll be the same thing, cuz we only have one version, and it's Python 3.14.
So we have a good version of Python now, and away we go.
So the next thing we're going to want to do is install a programmer editor.
And if you go in, go to this webpage,
www.py.4e.com/editors.php.
I can't update this video every few weeks.
Free open source programming text editors are difficult.
We've gone through a whole bunch of them.
I should probably add something to this page showing over the years all
the different editors that we have used.
I redo this video every time there's a new editor.
And brackets was the previous editor, but brackets has been turned into Phoenix code.
So here's a couple different choices you have.
You can use Phoenix code, which is the follow on to brackets.
And you can download and install it, and it's free and open source.
I find it a little complex.
But then the next one I'm going to recommend to you is Visual Studio.
This is free, not, I guess it is open source.
But it is extremely complex, but it's awesome in the fact that it has AI that
you can build in.
So sooner or later, professional programmers are going to be running
something like Visual Studio code with AI or whatever.
But the one I'm going to show you now is one that is very much free and
100% open source and simple.
And it actually builds a copy of Python into it that makes things really easy.
And so this is really great to get you started.
Eventually you can use anything.
If you have nothing, I think Thonny is the right thing to do.
So we're going to download it, boop, download this.
It's not very big, and now I'm going to install it.
Continue, continue, continue, install for all users.
Okay, I am going to enter the password offline, I mean off the screen.
Okay, so we're now done.
Now if you move the installer to the trash, so I'm going to,
I think I'm done with this for now, I'll make it a little smaller.
We'll go back to Python for everybody.
So the way this place got installed and the place a lot of things gets installed
is in your Macintosh hard drive under, and it's under Thonny.
But I like to go and just hit the Find button and type THONNY, and it finds it.
I hope it's the right one, Thonny in Applications.
I've been fiddling with it, this is the one I want, you'll only see one of them.
Then what I do is I go down here and I click on this, and I control click and
say Options Keep in Dock.
So then Thonny is down here, even when I run it.
First thing Thonny does is ask you what language you want, so
we'll tell it English.
Then Thonny goes through and
checks to see what things it needs to get permission.
So I don't know if it's going to ask me this time because it did not, but
it'll ask you some permissions.
So it's a little text editor, and I'm going to put, it's got Python syntax.
And then I can save this, and I'm going to save it to my desktop.
And then I'll make a new folder called py4e.
Now you'll notice that this desktop is the same as this desktop.
And now I'm in py4e, and I'm going to save this as first.py.
That's the program I'm going to name it.
So if I go into this py folder, you'll see that I got this.
I'm going to show this as a list.
You'll see I got this first.py, okay?
Now Thonny has a built-in programmer, a Python runner, and it's 3.10.
Maybe you'll get a later version of Thonny and have a later version of Python in it.
So I'm going to run it.
Now it wants me to allow, say yes to this, allow, ask yes to desktop.
Because I'm trying to run it, and it ran Hello World.
Now, eventually, you could use any text editor, and
they may or might have these runny things.
But I'd like to show you how programmers really do it.
We get into, so this is my desktop, oops.
And I'm, again, seeing the same desktop, and there's a folder here named py-free.
CD stands for Change Directory, py-free.
I can say, which directory am I in?
It's Printworking Directory, which is my home folder plus desktop plus py-free.
And then there's first.py.
Now, if you remember, we did Python 3 is in your path.
So you can type Python 3, And then you give it the file name, first.py.
And it runs, okay?
And so that is editing and
running your first Python programmer using Thonny and the terminal.
So I hope this has been useful to you as a walkthrough in Python for everybody.
I welcome you to the class.
And I encourage you to keep going, work towards becoming a master programmer.
This is the first step.
There's a lot of work, but I hope that we can make it fun for you, okay?
Cheers.
[MUSIC]